Arthur Taber Jones papers, 1876 - 1951 (bulk 1900 - 1950)
Smith College Archives
Arthur Taber Jones papers
1876 - 1951
1919 - 1950
Jones, Arthur Taber, 1876-1951
42
4 boxes ( 1.5 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Faculty. Professor of Physics. Contains correspondence, course materials, notes, research, reprints, and a scrapbook compiled by the Department of Physics in 1951.
Biographical Note
Arthur Taber Jones was born in Vassalboro, Maine on September 6, 1876. Shortly after receiving his B.S. from the University of Chicago in 1899 he joined the teaching staff at Purdue University (1902 - 1910). In 1904 he and Jane Johnson married. A daughter, Esther Elizabeth, was born in 1909. In 1911 he moved to Clark University and was awarded his Ph.D. in 1913. He spent several years at Iowa State College before joining Smith College in 1919.
A prolific researcher and a dedicated polyglot, Jones corresponded with amateur and professional researchers from all around the world. His interests spanned not only the field of acoustics for which he was widely known but also anything that caught his attention from the wheeling of a bicycle to the gliding motions of a snake. Jones' time at Smith is punctuated by many assignments and the rewards of a fruitful academic career: member and chair of many faculty committees, chair of the department, and president of the local chapters of the American Association of University Professors, Phi Beta Kappa, and Sigma Xi.
By the request of his department and the trustees of the college, he postponed his retirement and continued to teach through 1946 until his various colleagues returned from war work. He continued on as Professor Emeritus until his death on February 8, 1951.
After his death, Jones' colleagues in the Department of Physics went through nearly four decades worth of records and arranged for their transferal to the Neilson Library. The collection contains a wealth of intimate detail documenting scholarly discussions of moot points, interested inquiries, and heated debates as well as publications and reprints from international journals, independent publishers, commercial vendors and other unique sources.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Correspondence, publications, photographs, clippings, course notes, research notes, a scrapbook and other materials documenting Arthur Taber Jones' career as a professor of Physics at Smith College. The collection includes a substantial series of correspondence between Jones in his roles as professor, researcher, and editor as well as a materials collected by Jones relating to carillons and organs.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into three series:
General
Professional
Scrapbook
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The Arthur Taber Jones papers were created by Arthur Taber Jones and donated to the College Archives.
Jones, Arthur Taber, 1876-1951; Smith College. -- Department of Physics; Physics--Study and teaching; blueprints (reprographic copies); carillons; commercial correspondence; declaratory and advertising artifacts; editorial writers; formulas; personal correspondence
- Series I: General1900 - 1951
- Series II: Professional 1900 - 1950
  This series is arranged into a set of five (5) subseries:
  1.Notes
  2.Research
  3.Teaching
  4.Promotional Materials
  5.Correspondence
- Series III: Scrapbook 1900 - 1950
  Donated by the Department of Physics at the time of his death in 1951. This series is arranged into a set of three (3) subseries:
  1. Reprints and Articles on Sound
  2. In Memoriam Arthur Taber Jones, 1876 - 1951
  3. Various Subjects in Physics
- Series I: General
  - faculty file, 1919 - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - photographs, 1900 - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - projects, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Professional
  - Notes
    - The Vortex Motion Causing Edge Tones,1925 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - The Mechanism of Edge-Tone Production, 1925 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Self-Induced Vibrations, 1925 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Experimental Investigations on the Maintenance of Vibrations, 1925 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Uber die Wirbelbuildung bei Schneidentonen, 1925 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Research
    - The Hammond Organ, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Cornelia Gould Organ, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Chapter III. Scientific Principles - Theory of certain musical instruments, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Motion of a Bell and It's clapper, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - translation, Das Toeplersche schlierenverfahren, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Simpson Tuning Method, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Teaching
    - "Determination of the Accuracy of Pitches on Little Reed Organ in Lilly Hall by Means of Beats"; by Randall and Whittemore, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Determination of the Frequencies of the Just Seale on the Estey Reed Organ"; by Meaker, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Promotional Materials
    - The Spencer Steel Orgoblo, Organ Power Company, 1900 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - The Dayton C. Miller Collections relating to "The Flute", 1900 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Reverberation and the Organ, Etsey Organ Company, 1900 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Electronics in the Church, Schulmerich Electronics, 1900 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - The Skinner Organ, 1900 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Crescent Avenue Presbyterian Church, 1900 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - M.P. Moller Pipe Organs, 1900 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Orgelet I Tonder Kirke, Th. Frobenius and Co., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Casavant Organs, 1900 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Bochumer Verein fur Bergbau und Gubstahlfabrikation, 1900 - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence
    - Acoustical Society of America, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - American Standards Association, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Amherst College, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Ancient Accepted Scottish Rite, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Andrade, E.N .da C., 1944 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Arts, Jan, 1925 - 1944 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Bartholomew, William, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Biehle-Bautzen, Johannes, 1926 - 1932 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Bigelow, Arthur Lynds, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Blackwood, O. H., 1943 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Blueprints originals, various dates (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Bouckaert, A, 1926 - 1932 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Boyle, Malcolm, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Bragg, William, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Brunqardt, A.O., 1940 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Butler, Henry, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Cartmel, William, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Chapman, Seville, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Chase, Carl, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Conklin, William, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Cook, Samuel, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Crew, Henry, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Curtis Institute of Music, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Davidson, J.C., 1950 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Davis, Marian, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Denyn, Jef, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - District of Lewisham East, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Dorsey, Herbert Grove, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Duff, A. Wilmer, 1930 - 1943 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Eckart, Carl, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Edgerton, Harold E., 1941 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Edwards, Preston, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Estherbrook, Edith, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Ferry, Erwin, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - First Baptist Church, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Fishel, Adolph, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Fitzsimmons, A.W., 1931 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Fletcher, Harvey, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Flook, L.R., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Foley, Arthur, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Frank, Lester, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Franklin, Cyril, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Frederick, Halsey, 1930 - 1931 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Fulcher, Gordon, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - G.E. Stechart and Company, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Gaehr, Paul, 1937 - 1950 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - General Radio Company, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Giannini, G.W., 1932 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Gillett and Johnston Ltd., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Griesbacher, P., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Ham, Lloyd, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Hammond Organ, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Hastings, Charles, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Jefferson Avenue Presbyterian Church, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - John Taylor and Company, 1919 - 1930 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Jones, W. Bartlett, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Jordan, E.B., 1944 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Kanonikus Griesbacher, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - King, Louis, 1926 - 1930 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Klug, Heinz, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Kunerth, William, 1933 - 1950 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Kyoto Imperial University, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Langlade, E., 1934 - 1935 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Les fils de Georges Paccard, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Liberty Carillons, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Little, Noel, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Lloyd, Llewelyn, 1937 - 1950 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Lottermoser, Werner, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Matthews, W.L., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Meneely Bell Company, 1919 - 1935 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Meneely Bell Company, 1936 - 1946 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Meneely Bell Company, 1947 - 1950 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Merrill, George, 1922 - 1923 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Metropolitan Water and Sewage Board, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Meyer, Erwin, 1933 - 1949 (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Meyer, Frederick, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Meyerhoff, Howard, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - Miesse, C. Charles, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Miller, Dayton, 1920 - 1935 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - Miller, Julius, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Morse, Philip, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Morton, W.B., 1921 - 1926 (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - Mosauer, Walter, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - Mulaik, Stanley, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Nederlandse Klokkengieteru, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Nichols, J.R., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - Northrop, Paul, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - Novello and Company, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Ogilby, R.B., 1939 (Box 3, Folder 115)
    - Olds, 1926 - 1929 (Box 3, Folder 116)
    - Oxford University Press, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 117)
    - Pagon, W. Watters, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 118)
    - Peery, Paul, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 119)
    - Perkins, Henry A., 1943 - 1949 (Box 3, Folder 120)
    - Powers, Wallace, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 121)
    - Pratzel, Willy, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 122)
    - Redfield, John William, 1931 - 1932 (Box 3, Folder 123)
    - Rice, Gorham, 1926 - 1933 (Box 3, Folder 124)
    - Richards, Emerson, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 125)
    - Richardson, E.G., 1925 - 1942 (Box 3, Folder 126)
    - Riverbank Laboratories, 1930 - 1931 (Box 3, Folder 127)
    - Rockse, Frederick, undated (Box 3, Folder 128)
    - Roller, Duane, 1938 - 1947 (Box 3, Folder 129)
    - Russell, G. Oscar, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 130)
    - Sabin, Paul, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 131)
    - Saunders, Frederick, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 132)
    - Sehouten, J.F., 1939 - 1947 (Box 3, Folder 133)
    - Shook, G.A., 1940 (Box 3, Folder 134)
    - Slater, John, 1930 - 1931 (Box 3, Folder 135)
    - Sosman, Robert, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 136)
    - Stewart, G.W., 1923 (Box 3, Folder 137)
    - Stuber, G., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 138)
    - Szilard, Leo, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 139)
    - Taylor, Lloyd W., 1938 - 1943 (Box 3, Folder 141)
    - Thompson, Joseph, 1925 - 1933 (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - Torrey, G.S., 1932 (Box 3, Folder 143)
    - Trendelenburg, Ferdinand, 1947 - 1950 (Box 3, Folder 144)
    - Trinity Methodist Episcopal Church, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 145)
    - University of Chicago, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 146)
    - Van der Elst, W., 1926 - 1932 (Box 3, Folder 147)
    - Van Geyseghem, Victor, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 148)
    - Van Netta Studio, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 149)
    - Vas Nunes, Abraham, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 150)
    - Vittone, Piero, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 151)
    - Vlam, Chris, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 152)
    - Wachsmuch, Richard, 1934 - 1935 (Box 3, Folder 153)
    - Watson, F.R., 1917 (Box 3, Folder 154)
    - Watson, Lloyd, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 155)
    - Weyel, R.L., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 156)
    - Wickenden, Roger, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 157)
    - Williamson, Charles, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 158)
    - Wood, Irving, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 159)
    - Worrall Hospital, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 159)
    - Yale University, 1926 - 1931 (Box 3, Folder 160)
    - Young, Robert, 1939 - 1950 (Box 3, Folder 161)
- Series III: Scrapbook
  - Reprints and Articles on Sound
    - section I, 1914 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 162)
    - section II, 1914 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - In Memoriam Arthur Taber Jones, 1876 - 1951
    - section I, 1900 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 164)
    - section II, 1900 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 165)
    - section III, 1900 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 166)
    - section IV, 1900 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 167)
    - section v, 1900 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - Various Projects on Sound
    - section I, 1900 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 169)
    - section II, 1900 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 170)
    - section III, 1900 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 171)
    - section IV, 1900 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 172)